Guide to the Harold Roth Photograph Collection 1937-1950 PR 195
New-York Historical Society
Harold Roth Photograph Collection
1937-1950
New-York Historical Society
PR 195
1 Linear feet (1 box)
Collection consists of 25 gelatin silver photographic prints, documenting New York City street life. The photographs are digitized and available in the Shelby White and Leon Levy Digital Library.
Provenance
Purchase, 1991, 1996, and 1998.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to thirty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. See guidelines in Print Room for details.
Biographical Note
Born in 1918, New York photographer Harold Roth received his first camera in 1930, as a gift from Kodak to half a million children who turned twelve in the year of the fiftieth anniversary of George Eastman's first patent. By the late 1930s, Roth had graduated to a Graflex camera and begun to extensively document the city around him. He is best known for his photographs of 1940s and 1950s New York City street life.
Scope and Content Note
The Harold Roth Photograph Collection spans the period from 1937-1950 and consists of 25 black and white gelatin silver photographic prints, all 11 x 14 inches.
Photographs in this collection show New York City street life, and range from a group of children playing in the spray of an open fire hydrant in the waning sunlight to a view of foot traffic in Madison Square Park against the hazy backdrop of the Flatiron Building. Other views include the interior of Grand Central Terminal, a hot dog vendor at work, the Parachute Jump at Coney Island, and an aerial view of a stickball game. Several photographs of circuses and sideshows are also included.
The photographs in this collection were printed by Harold Roth from his vintage negatives between 1991 and 1995. Prints are numbered, captioned, and in most cases signed on the verso by Roth.
Arrangement
Photographs are arranged chronologically.
Existence and Location of Copies
Digital copies are available in the Shelby White and Leon Levy Digital Library.
Gelatin silver prints.; New York (N.Y.) -- Photographs; Street life -- New York (State) -- New York
- unspecified
  - Forest Avenue - the Bronx, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Big Snakes - 1939 World's Fair (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Circus Elephants, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Luna Park, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Parachute Jump - Coney Island, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Times Square, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Circus Side Show - Albany, N.Y., 1941 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Grand Central Station, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bowery and Houston St., 1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Flatiron Building, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Greenwich Village Antique Store, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Lower East Side Stable - Mangin Street, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Stick Ball Game, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Street Beach, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 3rd Ave. at 14th St., 1946 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Hot Dog Vendor, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Lamppost - Bowery and Canal St., 1947 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Williamsburg Bridge, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Boys on East River Pier - Manhattan Bridge, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Perrier Vintage 1948 South Street (2 copies) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 6th Ave. at 44th St., 1948 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - South St., 1948 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Water St., 1948 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - East River Drivers, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 5)